In this video I'm going to show you how to write a
beautiful thesis using latex and I don't mean the
actual content of the thesis that's up to you what
I mean here is how do you take that content put it
into a document and actually beautifully display
it for example this is my thesis and there's lots
of equations and paragraphs and figures structured
like bibliographies and references and appendices
how do you take all of that and make one beautiful
document so that's what we're going to talk about
in this video now if you're a complete beginner
to LaTeX that's totally fine I actually have two
previous videos that introduced LaTeX from the
very beginning so check those out down in the
description but in this video we're going to build
on that to talk about all the different components
that are relevant for writing a thesis now if
you're on the fence about whether you should
even use LaTeX for your thesis like do you want
to learn this whole markup language or do you
just want to try it with Microsoft word well
it depends a little bit on your discipline for
example I'm in mathematics and it's just standard
that pretty much everybody writes their theses in
mathematics because LaTeX is just so powerful for
being able to display equations but if you're in
many other disciplines I still encourage you to
try and consider writing LaTeX for your thesis
it's just so powerful at being able to tightly
control a consistent look over your entire thesis
to keep track of things like numbering and to have
a precise control over exactly how you want it to
look LaTeX is just totally worth it in my view
particularly for investing the time to actually
write a thesis now to get started in LaTeX you
need to have some sort of LaTeX editor now there's
a lot of LaTeX editors out there but the one that
I've really enjoyed for the last several years
is Overleaf and actually I'm really proud that
they have become the sponsor of today's video
because overleaf is one that you don't have
to install anything it's all based in your
web browser everything's stored inside of the
cloud and it just makes it so much easier to
learn and to create in LaTeX and it's up to you
as a completely free version which i actually
appreciate is really good like you can write your
entire thesis in LaTeX you don't need to upgrade
but it also has some really nice quality
of life upgrades like keeping track of a
whole bunch of different versions and
sharing with all of your collaborators
like for example your thesis advisors and so for
me at least upgrading to the paid versions is
totally worth it but but I'll leave that choice up
to you okay with those preliminaries said and done
let's get into the video before i even create a
new project I'm actually just going to create a
new folder here I'll call this youtube and this
allows me to put everything related to a thesis
which might be many many different files all in
one nice folder come up here and we are going to
start a brand new project and there's a couple
options we're actually in this video going to
use a blank project like we're going to start from
the beginning and I'm going to show you how to do
everything but it's often nice if you scroll down
here you can see some of the templates that are
available on the Overleaf website so for example
for thesis if I show the gallery of all items your
university may well have a template already so for
example i did my PhD at the University of Toronto
and i can just click this here to import the
university of Toronto standard thesis with all
the requirements for formatting already in there
so definitely check out the gallery to see if your
university is here or if there's just a template
you really like so for the purpose of this video
we're gonna go and just click on a blank project
and let's call it youtube thesis all right this
is a wonderful phd thesis that we're going to have
I'm going to hide the left-hand menu for now and
what i want to notice is that there's two sides
to this on the left-hand side we get our code
and then when we click the compile button it
spits out well what it's going to look like and
right now you have almost nothing so there's
a few things I'm going to do right off the bat
the document class is currently default set
to be article and I'm going to change this to
report and when i compile that already it changes
the look and feel there's a title page here and
then we have this beginning section which is
called introduction it appears on a new page
basically reports are designed for longer
documents than just an article was there's
other classes like book which is reasonable as
well but I'm going to use report now the first
thing i want to do is I'm going to change this
title which i have as youtube thesis that was
the name of the document and that's totally fine
but i want to add perhaps a university there so
I'm going to open a new section of braces here
I'm going to give it the size and there's lots
of different sizes you can do I'm going to choose
\Large which is actually a little bit smaller than
the size i set for the youtube thesis already and
I'm going to call it the university of youtube the
most prestigious university in the world and we
get youtube thesis and then university of youtube
i don't like that that's all in one line
so I'm going to come to youtube thesis
the double backslash allows me to end the line and
i have a slightly better title now i can make this
title page look fancier and nicer but that's what
we have for right now and i want to notice that
the actual body of the thesis is all going to go
between the begin document and the end document
the only two things i have there right now is
a section called \maketitle which just makes
the title page that's what the purpose is all of
that data that was collected here above the begin
document now that's turned into a title page and
then i have this new section and if i scroll down
here i can see this new section okay now the
first thing i want to do is I'm actually going
to get rid of this section here this introduction
we're going to deal with that a little bit later
because in a thesis there's usually a few things
that happen before the introduction and the first
of those is the abstract so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to set backslash chapter and
because i do not want my abstract and other things
that go ahead of the main body of the thesis like
a dedication and acknowledgement because i don't
want those to have chapter numbers i go \chapter*
and the star just says don't give this a chapter
number then I'm going to go and give abstract
and we can type whatever our thesis is going to be
about i can scroll down and now i have a section
called abstract which contains a little bit
of content probably it would be a little
bit longer if you're trying to write a whole phd
thesis same basic idea i can do the same chapter
with the star to say i don't want enumerated
maybe i want to make it a dedication page
and i can say oh you know for my subscribers
and maybe i would also like to have a
chatper let's change that chapter that's better a
chapter that's going to be called acknowledgements
overleaf by the way here is really nice it has
a spell checker built in so you see how it's
got the red line here saying there's something
wrong i right click and i can just do my spell
check so it's got those sort of like slightly
nicer features that surprisingly a lot of LaTeX
editors still don't have nevertheless i want to
thank and then you can fill that in okay so let's
compile that overleaf actually has a pretty cool
feature if you get tired clicking this recompile
button you can come down and click auto compile
on and it's just going to regularly be doing that
but basically does the equivalent of clicking
that button for you but regardless we have our
title page we have our abstract and we have our
dedication and then finally our acknowledgements
and that's all before we get to the body of the
thesis which is empty i really like using folders
because if you can think about a thesis it's going
to get really really long and if i try to put
the entire thesis in this one document like every
single thing I'm ever going to have in the thesis
is all in one document it's going to be too
much it's just going to be extremely long
so one of the things i like to do over here is
come and make separate chapters in separate files
that allows you to move the chapters around and
just open up one chapter and just deal with that
and only compile one chapter at once if you so
choose so what I'm going to do is in my folder I'm
going to click a new file and I'm going to call it
how about ch for chapter and then I'll see a I'll
say something like ch-youtubebuttons or something
silly like this and this creates this other tech
file not the main.tex file it's in a separate
one let's make another one like uh chapter
i don't know subscribers I'm just sort of using
youtube words as the the standard names here
and if i open one of these they're just blank
documents so if i want to actually fill them
in i have to add something so I'm going to make
this one how about this is going to be a \chapter
and in this chapter i actually want it to be
enumerated i want it to be chapter one so I'm
not going to put the star there and so I'm going
to call it youtube buttons and maybe this chapter
has three different sections it's going to have
one section called the subscribe button it's going
to have a section called the like button and uh oh
yeah i know we have a section on the notification
bell all the good youtube stuff okay so let's
go in there and compiling so now what's happened
well in the document there's no notion of this i
mean i don't i can scroll up and down through my
document i don't see it so what i have to do is to
make this connected with my document i go back to
main okay so what i type is \include and i really
love this about overleaf it's so smart because
it pops down this contextual menu of all the
different things that i might want to include well
i have two different tex files that are chapters
the subscribers and the youtube buttons ones
so I'm going to click the youtube buttons one
because that's the one I've added content to
I'm going to wait for it to recompile and it tells
me that i have an error i really like this about
overleaf so i had that error I'm going to click
and try to figure it out it says i suspect you
have forgotten a closing curly brace and this
happened at the spot \include
so let's go to that thing and see what's going
on here and indeed right there chapter youtube
buttons i never put that closed curly brace on
it so now when i recompile thank you overleaf
for showing me those error messages and explain to
me what my silliness was i get my abstract i get
my dedication i get my acknowledgements and now i
have chapter one the youtube buttons chapter which
includes these three sub sections the subscribe
button like button and the notification bell
and what i really want to notice here is how much
is being done automatically by LaTeX. LaTeX is
choosing this enumeration chapter 1 and 1.1 1.2
1.3 it's choosing all of this style now if you
don't like any of the style there's ways to tweak
all of it if you don't think this is the look that
you're going for we can tweak all of this but
the point is you can tweak it in one place and
it's going to infect the entire document and the
style of everything it's not like you're going and
increasing the font size at one spot that you
might forget about later on and be inconsistent
about okay so that's my beginning let's just
keep on going i better add at least something
to this subscribers.tex file I'll make this a
new uh chapter called how i got 100k subscribers
and I'll say section and I'll call it make
funny youtube puns this is clearly the the
main trick and this is not connected so I've got
to go back to that main I've got the chapter on
youtube buttons I'll go \include again overleaf is
going to pop up the options and when i scroll down
i have this other chapter how i made 100
subscribers by doing funny youtube puns
so you can make as many chapters as you want you
can reorder them however you wish it just makes it
really really easy now as you get lots of chapters
and lots of sections you very well will want
an actual table of contents so let me show you
how you do this so what i have on the left is i
have these three chapters that I'm including in
the main.tex file and then I've included these
external chapters where most of my thesis is going
to be so the standard spot that you put your table
of cons is actually after your acknowledgements
here the command we want to use here is backslash
table of contents and if i compile this okay
let's see what happens well i have this nice
table of contents it shows me chapter one is
my youtube buttons chapter it's got those three
different sections chapter two is my how i got
100k subscribers and it has its particular section
you can see he's keeping track of the page numbers
here so page five page six and so forth now while
we're talking about chapters uh let's do a couple
more things I'm gonna make a conclusions chapter
nothing particularly fancy I'm just gonna \chapter
and conclusions you can choose to enumerate this
one or not it's a little bit up to you and then
I'm also going to make one the thing that often
goes after a conclusion is appendices and
dependencies are pretty much the same thing so I'm
going to write an appendix sometimes you're going
to have multiple things like appendix a appendix b
I'm just going to do one here and for the appendix
it looks just like a chapter at least for now
so I'm going to go chapter and I'll call
this one appendix so I've added two things
the conclusion and the appendix I'm going to
go back to main now look what i do for this
i want to include these into my document so I'm
going to go \include and I'm going to first add
that conclusions button nothing that happens much
there but i want to do something for the appendix
and the idea is i want to separate what chapters
are thought of as the main part of the thesis and
what chapters are thought of at the appendix so
to separate these i write backslash appendix and
now when i include a chapter it's going to be just
interpreted a little bit different so let's do the
exact same thing I'm going to include the appendix
thank you overly for popping this out and let me
go and compile everything and watch what happens
to the table of contents the conclusion was given
a chapter because i didn't put the star in the
\chapter it now is given a chapter number it's
chapter three according to this enumeration but
look at appendix appendix starts at a so the trick
is that when you went over here and used this
\appendix it basically resets the enumeration
and turns it to using alphabetical enumeration not
numerical enumeration so now i have this appendix
a and i could have appendix bcd and so forth now
i want to share with you a couple of overleaf's
premium features that just are extremely extremely
nice the first of these is just the ability to
have a whole bunch of collaborators if you want
to have a whole bunch of collaborators like
you've got a whole research team with you or you
have multiple different advisors who are on your
thesis committee well then it's really nice just
be able to share it with them so this is entirely
possible with overleaf you just add whoever it
is that you want to be and you can decide whether
they're going to be able to edit it or they're
just going to be able to read it and then they
can just contribute into your document the other
feature and i think this one is so incredibly nice
is the ability to go and look at your history so
i can come here and you can see on the right hand
side here i have a lot of different changes and
i can go back to previous states of my different
sections of my different documents so for example
i was just created recently i was playing around
with the youtube button one so if i if i open the
top one it looks exactly like we had it before
if i go to chapter youtube buttons from a while
ago okay back on 1:55 pm now i get the version of
it that doesn't have all that stuff with figures
so if i want to go back in the past and figure
out what's happening well then i can do that i can
compare this to a different version i can label my
version so i can sort of keep track of them and it
makes it very nice for over the course of years of
developing a thesis for you to figure out like
what's happening there's no worry you're gonna
accidentally delete something crucial and you'll
have missed something that you worked on years ago
you have your history you're safe okay so that's
the basic structure but let's try adding some
content and perhaps the most important thing is
any figures that you might make how do we deal
with that now in the previous video on LaTeX I've
talked about just creating a figure before but
i really want to talk more about figure management
how do i deal with having lots of figures in this
particular video so what I'm going to do is I'm
come up I'm going to make a new subfolder and this
is going to be called images and so here it is
i can go inside of my images and i have this new
folder then if i click on it I'm going to upload
and let me go and find some images I've created
three images already like notification
and subscribe and I'm going to open them
and they're loaded in and now if i expand
my images i have my three files there now
to actually get these images into your document
i actually need to use a new package so I'm back
here in main.tex and I'm going to do \include
excuse me not include i want to use \usepackage
and I'm going to use one called graphicx with an x
at the end this is the same one I've talked about
in my previous video it just allows me to include
nice figures now the place I'm going to go is in
my chapter on youtube buttons and the command here
is going to be backslash \begin and i want
to just let overleaf expand all the different data
and so let's come along and put this in there's
a few things in here you need to fill in so the
first of them is going to be where's your actual
image and so if i expand what my images were i
have my different buttons I'm in the subscribe
button one so let me go and write it this way
right i go inside my brackets and i go images and
as you see it's already started starting to pop
it up and I'm going to go to the subscribe button
then i need to give it some sort of caption and
I'm going to call the caption the subscribe button
i need to give it a label this is so that you can
internally reference it let's call it subscribe
I've talked about how to internally reference
it before and all right there we go let's go
and see what this looks like so going to number
one you see that it says subscribe button like
button notification bell and then i have this
image down at the bottom and you might be like
hold on i don't want that image down at the bottom
here because it's sort of weird here that with the
three sections in a row they all have no content
they all go and then the image that is meant to be
associated with the subscribe button and the issue
here is if you don't do anything else then LaTeX
is going to automatically position your fingers
in a nice place in the document opposed to maybe
exactly where you want it so i can fix this by
adding a parameter to the \begin something
i haven't talked about previously I'm going to go
and do in brackets the [h] command this parameter
h just means here there's other ones like [t]
which has the top of the page or [b] which is the
bottom of the page now if i recompile it with that
little extra bit there the button appears exactly
where i want let me copy everything and I'm going
to do basically the same thing for the like button
basically the same for the subscribe button but
I'm just going to turn to change the names okay
i think I've cleaned everything up let's compile
that and i believe i now have a subscribe button
looks nice a like button looks nice a notification
bell and then it appears in the middle of the page
now LaTeX is actually a little bit not liking of
this it gives me a bit of a view warning that says
maybe it'll be better to specify it as [ht]
which stands for here and top if possible it
doesn't like that and so i can come here on
that one since it seems to be causing a bit
of a problem and it will take this error message
away it's not going to display it because again
there's just no content on the next page so it's
just going to nicely put it in the middle just to
keep everything nice and centralized and what i
really like about it is that the enumeration like
figure 1.1 and 1.2 here these are which by the
way these are being enumerated at the level of
chapters right now it's just a coincidence that i
have one one image per section but they're being
enumerated at the level of chapters uh i might
want to have a lot of these in my document and
i want to keep track of them somehow so what
i can do is i can go back over here to main
and right underneath my table of contents i can go
\listofigures and if i do that it's going to have
this nice way to underneath so here's my list
of figures right there table of contents then
list of figures and you can see exactly where
they're going to be so this is very convenient
you can do the same kind of idea you could have a
list of tables or other different items and in a
long thesis having these organizational structural
components can just make it a lot nicer for you
or for the reader of your thesis to be able to
figure out what's going on all right we're doing
well uh i think i want to now turn to one of the
most interesting parts which is the bibliography
so I'm going to expand so i can see my list of
files one more time and what I'm going to do here
is i want to create a new file and I'm going to
call it my references but normally all of my files
have been .tex files I'm going to call this one
a .bib file for bibliography and bibliographies
are the one major part of a thesis they're just a
little bit different we're gonna have a different
type of file not a text file a .bib file so
I'm gonna create that and it appears down here
so if i go into this I'm actually just copying and
pasted from one i have found online I'm going to
copy and paste Einstein's special relativity paper
and what i want to notice is that your dot bib
file it doesn't impose the type of formatting the
file is just collecting information this is the
author this is the title this is the journal this
is the year and what that means is is that you're
not spending a whole bunch of time precisely
formatting exactly how your bibliography works
the way you might on Microsoft word where
you're like this has to be bolded and this
has to be underlined you're just collecting the
data here and there's a standard way to do this
now figuring out the exact syntax for how you
collect the data for making these bibliography
files is actually not going to be done in this
video but I'm going to put a detailed link from
overlink down in the description so you can see
exactly how to do this personally i actually think
that you shouldn't manually create your .bib files
because overleaf actually syncs with a number of
external bibliography software things like zotero
where you can be collecting all of the references
for your thesis in one spot and it's going to
make these bib files for you so I'm going to put
the information to that down in the description
and basically say go and figure out how to make
your bibliography files what i will cover though
is now that I've made this bibliography file
how do i actually put it back into my document
so as usual I'm going to go back to the main my
bibliography is going to be after my appendix here
and there's going to be two different components
to it the first thing is i need to specify the
style so I'm going to say \bibliographystyle
and you have a lot of options here because
bibliographies can be formatted in many different
ways there's many different styles and your
university may have a specific one that it wants
I'm just going to use a plain one because it's
just nice and i don't know not a plane without
an e at the end uh because it's just a nice and
simple so that just sets the style it's basically
saying how do you interpret that dot bib file to
display it nicely again there's lots of different
standards here then I'm going to say bibliography
and well there's only one bibliography file that
we have it's the one called reference so
my bibliography is this ref file I'm going
to compile that and let's see what we have now
there's one little thing which is when i go to
this it doesn't look like there's anything there
i mean if i go to my ref i had this reference for
einstein but there's nothing in the bibliography
and the reason is that i haven't used that
particular reference in my document so okay where
should i go let's go to the subscriber chapter say
and i don't know why in making youtube buttons
we would talk about special relativity but i can
reference say einstein and the way i do this is as
follows i go \cite and then notice that overleaf
is looking through your files here it says the
only thing you can really cite here is einstein
and i'm going oops i didn't mean to hit back
or the period there i'll put the period there
now when i compile it it will change in two
places the first thing here is that under
the bibliography i have used that einstein
bibliography reference and so there it is the
second thing is if i scroll back up to my chapter
2 see what happens i can reference einstein and
then it says a little one there one referring
to the fact that you've got a one down there
this is what is so nice about LaTeX everything
you just kept track of right as you change the
number of citations throughout your document
all of that enumeration will be completely
automatic everything will link up appropriately
and you'll be able to deal with your references
i want to show you one final really nice killer
feature about overleaf if you click this review
button and this is really just pretty special to
overleaf i'm going to go it says track changes
is off I'm going to click this toggle
and now track changes is going to be on
and so imagine i come along here and do something
and I'll get rid of that panel and let me imagine
i do something like i am going to expand
this now when you have this track changes on
you get to see what is the new thing that you are
doing right now as you're adding to your document
and indeed if i click on this review i
can come along and make a change like
for example one of your collaborators
can be like i think you should add this
and now you have the option to just choose do
you want to accept it or do you want to reject it
and so this is one of the killer features of
overleaf that allows to have multiple people
collaborating on the same document or even just
yourself you want to see what you've been doing
at your different iterations of writing and
allows you to track all those changes it's like
the history but on steroids all right the next
thing i want to talk about is how do we deal with
footnotes I'm going to make a new line over here
and i want to do a footnote right here okay so
let me say that i want to have something that
appears at the bottom of the page I'm going to go
backslash and I'm going to say \footnote i know
shocker and then i write in whatever it is this is
like i don't know this is my first
footnote very exciting okay let's run that
now i had to figure out where in our document
I'm going to be i believe i was in chapter
2 here so there it is i can reference einstein
I've done that first then it says i want to do
a footnote right here and you'll notice it says i
want to do a footnote right here it puts a little
bit of a one with different formatting than the
formatting for references again there are ways
to change all of these looks if you so wish
but this is how it's done it sort of natively
and then down at the bottom this is my first
footnote now if i have a really long footnote i
might not want to define it right in the middle of
some other sentence or it might be the case that i
want to refer to the same footnote multiple times
in a row and i can do that with something called
\footnotemark so i can use \footnote mark to
make a placeholder and not define it until later
then to define it later I'll do \footnotetext and
this is saying what is the text of that footnote
and i will say this is my second footnote and
let's see what happens when i do it i can use two
notice that there's a space here so it looks a
little bit weird i really prefer to have that
there so that the 2 is right on top of the use
that looks a little better now the now the 2 is
right beside the use but then i didn't define
it to later if i go down at the bottom this is
my first note footnote and this is my second
footnote and then if you want to have multiple
marks for the same footnote i can use this command
it's \footnotemark and then it goes inside of a
parameter it puts in \value so it just
says put in the same reference basically that you
had before and if i do that now I'm going to get
that 2 twice so you see how there's i can use 2
and then until later 2 the same 2 is referred to
here and then it's defined to be whatever this
footnote text is now the final thing i want
to do is talk about how can i organize the
layout of the entire thesis things like margins on
the left and the right and the top and the bottom
as well as dealing with things like printing
so the first thing I'm going to do is go
back to the very beginning where it said document
class and i included a report but I'm going to put
inside of my square brackets that allows it to
feed into parameter I'm going to write [twoside]
and first of all i just think you should always be
printing your thesis two-sided just to save paper
and this just allows that to be done this way
to note that there's going to be two different
sides to this you could also use a spot to make
the font larger or smaller or you can add many
extra different parameters to this document
class here now i have to add a new package to
deal with margins I'm going to use the following
packets use packages called the geometry package
and i can specify now all of my margins
within here so I'm going to copy and paste
uh something called new geometry and i specified
the top to be three quarters of an inch the bottom
to be three quarters of an inch in order to
be three quarters of lynch and the inner to be
specified as 1.5 inches this is also a spot
where you might want to change what type of
paper so for example it defaults to letter but if
you want a4 or legal you can specify all of this
with the geometry package now I'm going to do and
then I'm going to do one thing i haven't actually
written a lot of text anywhere so I'm going to
add a generic uh it's kind of a funny one that
people who use LaTeX a lot do it's called lipsum
and lipsum is just a package that has a generic
large amount of text I'll show you what i mean and
then I'm going to go down here \lipsum and then in
square brackets I'll write 1 to 20. so this is
just going to give the first i think 20 lines of
this let's see what it looks like well here's the
following it's just a whole bunch of i guess this
is latin text and this is just a trick to be able
to generate well a lot of text so you can sort of
see what it looks like now that i have a bunch of
text there this will be your actual content there
it nicely does this indenting of the first line
when it's trying to make paragraphs but notice the
difference i mean i I've now zoomed out so you can
see the whole thing notice how the margin on the
left is way smaller than the margin on the right
this despite the fact that if i go back to my main
tech file here and basically what's happened here
is that the i specified the outer margin to be
0.75 an inch and the inner margin to be 1.5 and
that's because i said it was two-sided so i want
when you put it two-sided together and you look
at it say it's been nicely binded into the book
that inner margin here will be 0.75 plus the other
0.75 to the 1.5 inches so basically on this page
this is going to be an inner margin that's going
to be an outer margin let's go down one page it's
exactly reversed outer margin and inner margin
this allows you to print it into some binded
document and on the columns will look really
nice the exact amounts of these margins please
do look up your university specifications here but
this geometry package allows you to control them
now there is a lot more that i can tell you
about and one of the things I've been doing
in this particular video and the previous ones is
not using a huge amount of packages packages are
all these little extra things that you can add
that give new functionality and so in the next
video I'm going to share with you a bunch of my
favorite packages that i use all the time that i
think can really superpower your LaTeX documents
and make them just awesome allow you to customize
so many of the different things and just make
it that much more pretty so that and more coming
up in the next video and if you enjoyed this one
please do give it a like for the youtube algorithm
if you have any questions or thoughts about
LaTeX leave them down in the comments below
all the links to many of the different topics
that I've talked about are down in the description
check out overleaf this is a long call to action
and we'll do some more math in the next video!